Guide to the Fordyce family papers, 1839-1979
Fordyce family papers, 1839-1979
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Fordyce Family papers, 1839-1979
3646
Fordyce family
30.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, account books, notebooks, photographs, deeds, field notes, glass slides, newsclippings, daguerrotypes, portraits, photograph albums, wallpaper samples, menus, invitations, stock certificates, and scrapbooks.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of correspondence, account books, notebooks, photographs, deeds, and other material of the Fordyce family of Scipio Center, Cayuga County and Monroe County, New York. Also contains papers of the Ohio branch of the Fordyce family, which included George Lincoln Fordyce, a Cleveland businessman and naturalist.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of correspondence, account books, notebooks, photographs and deeds of the Fordyce family of Scipio Center, Cayuga County and Monroe County, New York. Includes letters and papers of the Nathaniel Horton Fordyce family of Monroe County, New York, 1839-1925, 1969. Many of them are letters to Nathaniel and Henrietta's daughter, Cornelia, a schoolteacher, from sisters Helen, Frances and Mary, her brother Horton and from Henrietta. Also, courtship letters of Horton (Nathaniel Horton, Jr.) Fordyce to Julia Heusner of Rochester, New York, and other letters from Heusner and Fordyce friends and relatives, 1846-1919. Includes letters to Cornelia Fordyce from family and friends, 1851-1919, some written by cousins fighting in the Civil War, 1861-1864; letters from Addie Gilson to Cornelia Fordyce, 1877-1907; photocopies of letters, papers and clippings concerning the Ohio branch of the Fordyce family, 1890-1979; correspondence includes letters from Ernest Thompson Seton, field notes, glass slides, articles, and clippings, largely concerning ornithology, by and about George Lincoln Fordyce, a Cleveland businessman and naturalist. Also, daguerreotypes, portraits and photographs of family members and friends; photograph albums, newspaper clippings; wallpaper samples from the Fordyce house; menus, invitations, postcards and stock certificates; letters, scrapbooks and photographs from the travels of Oscar F. and Rebecca Fordyce Gayton.
INDEX TO SERIES III BY AUTHOR WITH INCLUSIVE DATES OF CORRESPONDENCE
Adams, Alice
1866-1876, 1880
Adams, Alice B.
Adams, Athalia
Adriance, Mrs. George (Ernestine Knapp)
1909
Baldwin, Stephen
1853 or 1855
Bannister, F.C.
1874-1875
Bennett, Alma C.
1855
Bennett, Mrs. C.D. (Charles D.)
1884
Bloomfield, Nellie
1863-1865
Brown, S.S.
1896, 1898
Carpenter, Frank
1862
Chapin, W.D.
1882
Clark, Sally
1866
Clements, L.
1871
Collins, Florence K.
1899, 1901-1902
Collins, Blanche
1903-1904
Collins, Laura Horrigan
1904
Collins, Ada Horrigan
1905
Conover, V.
n.d.
Culver, M.J.A.
n.d.
Cornell University
1875
Davis, W.P.
1872-1873
Davis, Horace W.
1873-1874
Davis, Franklin
1875-1877
Decker, Martha and Delia
1851-1867
Douglas, Franklin
1889
Ewing, Lizzie E.
1875
Fordyce, Samuel Wesley
1861-1863
Galusha, Esther (McCollum)
1869
Gifford, Mariette (Chapin)
1867, 1869
Granger, L.H.
1876
Gunning, Frank T.
1886 or 1889 or n.d.?
Harmon, Mrs. E.L.
1889
Heath, David W.
1871
Henderson, David N.
1872
Herslinger, Mamie
1884
Hunt, William
1862
Jones, William E.
1861-1862, 1869
Knapp, Elizabeth
1877-1881
McGee, Josephine
1860, 1862
Miller, Belle
1885
Miller, George
Morris, Mathilda
1860
Morris, Carrie
?
Morris, Lauretta
?
Olney, Eunice Jane or Jennie (later Tobey)
n.d., 1851-1852, 1854-1861, 1867, 1881, 1886-1891, 1894, 190?, 1909
Orchard, Katie
1904, 1908
Page, Mrs. A.H.
1873-1874
Patterson, Harley M.
1861
Patterson, Harvey J.
1862-1865
Patterson, Hannah
1861-1865, 1874, 1876
Patterson, Anna C.
1868, 1869, 1878-1880, 1884
Quirk, Mrs. J.A.
1879
Scott, William
1900
Shorkley, A.F. (Amelia)
1879
Smith, Belle M.
1899
Stratton, Eliza
ca. 1869, ca. 1870, 1871-1873, ca. 1886, 1887, 1889, 1890, 1892
Strong, Gail
1896, 1900
Strong, Ida
1903, 1905
Strong, Frances
1906, 1907
Strong, Cora
1904
Strong, H.L.
1910
Van Dusan, Phebe Martha
1869, 1870, 1873
Van Dusan, Gertrude F.
1882-1883, 1887-1888
Van Dusan, Edith
1869
McKay, Edith
1889, 1891-1892, 1894, 1896
McKay, Willard
1899, 1901, 1907
McKay, Mildred
1904, 1909, 1913
Warner, Rilla
1869
Watkins, Ada D.
1881-1882
Wayte, Aldred H.
1872
Wayte, Edwin
1872
Wayte, Mrs. E.
1885-1886
Welch, Ella or Ellen
1865-1866
Whitaker, ?
1904
Willard, Frances
n.d.
Willard, M. Mary
1864-1865
Willard, M.J.
1889, 1905
Wilmarth, Jane
1856
Wing, Mary (see Willard)
Weeks, Frances (Jones)
1906-1907
Unidentified
ca. 1850, 1871, 1874, 1880, 1889, 1908, n.d.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fordyce family.; Fordyce, Cornelia.; Fordyce, Frances.; Fordyce, George Lincoln.; Fordyce, Helen.; Fordyce, Henrietta.; Fordyce, Horton (Nathaniel Horton); Fordyce, Mary.; Fordyce, Nathaniel Horton.; Seton, Ernest Thompson.; Gayton, Oscar F.; Gayton, Rebecca Fordyce.; Gilson, Addie.; Heusner, Julia.
Subjects:
Ornithology.; Voyages and travels.; Naturalists.
Places:
Cayuga County (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Monroe County (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Ohio--Social life and customs.; Scipio Center (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.
Form and Genre Terms:
Albums.; Daguerreotypes.; Menus.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Scapbooks.; Stock certificates.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
This collection has been divided into parts by the donor; each is described below. The donor has made transcriptions of the first four parts plus two parts not included in the collection. There are photocopies of other papers also not included. Each part is arranged chronologically; the transcriptions are generally arranged alphabetically by author, and chronologically.
Letters and papers of the Fordyce family are housed in 6-3" legal size Hollinger boxes. The collection also includes 2-4" legal size boxes of portraits, photographs and albums, daguerreotypes; and 1-16" box containing five looseleaf notebooks of transcriptions.
SERIES LIST
Series I, 1839-1925, 1969, consists of the letters and papers of the Nathaniel Horton Fordyce family of Monroe County, New York, and of a few friends and relatives. Many of the letters are to Nathaniel and Henrietta Fordyce's daughter, Cornelia, a schoolteacher, from sisters Helen, Frances, and Mary, and brother Horton, and from Henrietta.
Boxes 1-2.
Series II, 1846-1919, is mostly the courtship letters of Horton (Nathaniel Horton, Jr.) to Julia Heusner of Rochester, whom he married in 1896. In them he discusses the progress of the rooms he is adding to the farmhouse at Scipio for their own use. (Julia died in 1898 in childbirth.) Other letters are from Heusner and Fordyce friends and relatives.
Box 3
Series III, 1851-1913. These letters are from more than fifty friends and relatives to Cornelia Fordyce. A few letters, 1861-1864, are written by cousins at the battlefront. The transcripts of these letters are alphabetically arranged by sender.
Boxes 4-5.
Series IV, 1877-1907. Addie Gilson is the author of this extensive correspondnce--she wrote at least weekly to Cornelia--filled with thoughts on religion, her infirmities, and news of various family members and friends. Addie apparently was confined to a wheelchair much of the time. Beside writing many letters, she used her time in bottling and distributing "Dr. Hammond's Great Remedy."
Boxes 5-10.
Series V, ca. 1890 and later, is transcriptions only and concerns the "Ohio Fordyces." It includes photocopies of papers and letters and newsclippings, and narratives by the donor about family members; also articles by and about George L. Fordyce, businessman and noted Cleveland naturalist.
Boxes 11-20.
(Appendix #1-6, looseleaf notebook, includes supplementary material, miscellany, notes for Part VI, copies of a few pages of Benjamin Fordyce's account book.)
Series VI. Additional papers. Louise G. Coulson material.
Boxes 21-43.
(Note: Boxes 21-26, 28, and 49 transferred to the Cayuga County Historical Society, July 2018.)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I, 1839-1925, 1969.
  Consists of the letters and papers of the Nathaniel Horton Fordyce family of Monroe County, New York, and of a few friends and relatives. Many of the letters are to Nathaniel and Henrietta Fordyce's daughter, Cornelia, a schoolteacher, from sisters Helen, Frances, and Mary, and brother Horton, and from Henrietta.
  - 1839-1851 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1853-1856 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1860-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1866-1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1870 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1871 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1872, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1874 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1875 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1876 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1878, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1880 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1881 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1882, 1884, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1886, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1888, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1890-1899 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1901-1922, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series II, 1846-1919.
  Mostly the courtship letters of Horton (Nathaniel Horton, Jr.) to Julia Heusner of Rochester, whom he married in 1896. In them he discusses the progress of the rooms he is adding to the farmhouse at Scipio for their own use. (Julia died in 1898 in childbirth.) Other letters are from Heusner and Fordyce friends and relatives.
  - 1846, 1871, 1877-1887 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1888-1892 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1893-1895 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jan.-Apr. 1896 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - May 1896 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - June-July 1896 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Aug.-Sept. 1896 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Oct.-Dec. 1896 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jan.-June 1897 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - July-Dec. 1897 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jan.-Mar. 1898 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Apr. 1898-1919 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series III, 1851-1913.
  These letters are from more than fifty friends and relatives to Cornelia Fordyce. A few letters, 1861-1864, are written by cousins at the battlefront. The transcripts of these letters are alphabetically arranged by sender.
  - 1851-1854 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1855-1859 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1860, 1861 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1862, 1863 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1864-1866 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1867-1869 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1870-1873 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1874-1879 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1880-1886 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1887-1888 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1889-1899 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1900-1904 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1905-1913 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series IV, 1877-1907.
  Addie Gilson is the author of this extensive correspondnce--she wrote at least weekly to Cornelia--filled with thoughts on religion, her infirmities, and news of various family members and friends. Addie apparently was confined to a wheelchair much of the time. Beside writing many letters, she used her time in bottling and distributing "Dr. Hammond's Great Remedy."
  - 1877-1878 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1879 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1880 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1881 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1882-1886 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1887 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1888 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1889 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1890 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1891-1892 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1893-1894, 1898, 1900, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Daguerreotypes, portraits, photographs of family members and friends. (Box 7)
  - Two paragraph albums, photos, portraits, newspaper clippings of family members and friends. (Box 8)
  - Letter transcriptions. Five looseleaf notebooks: Part I, Part II, Part III, Parts IV and V, Appendix. (Box 9)
  - Envelopes, temporarily housed with the collection. (See Accession Sheet) (Box 10)
- Series V, ca. 1890 and later.
  Transcriptions only and concerns the "Ohio Fordyces." It includes photocopies of papers and letters and newsclippings, and narratives by the donor about family members; also articles by and about George L. Fordyce, businessman and noted Cleveland naturalist.
  - Mr. & Mrs. O.F. Gayton's travel literature and itineraries, c. 1950's. (Box 11)
  - George L. Fordyce's ornithological files: corres. and observations, corres. With Ernest T. Seton and photographs. (Box 12)
  - O.F.G. travel material, stock certificates, clippings re Fordyce Dept. Store, c. 1930's, other clippings include L.G. Coulson, wallpaper samples from Fordyce house, file of David Scollan's on N.Y.S. sugar beet growing. (Box 13)
  - G.L.F.'s ornithological papers include field diary, 1903-1905; corres. Of O.F. and D.C. Gayton and typescripts (3 paper boxes), c. 1904-1929, include Alvord, Cooper and Fischer relatives, and travel postcards. (Box 14)
  - Mr. & Mrs. O.F.G's letters and typescripts (Part IV), c. 1895-1959; printed items, slate blackboard, items of Louise Coulson. (Box 15)
  - G.L.F.'s photographs, glass slides and colored printed pictures of birds. (Box 16)
  - Case of glass slides of birds. (Box 17)
  - G.L.F.'s ornithological corres. And observations, corres. With E.T. Seton, and scrapbook of sports clippings. (Box 18)
  - Glass slides [foldered, box only partly full] (Box 19)
  - O.F.G. corres. And typescripts, photograph albums. [Box mostly foldered]. (Box 20)
  - Black case containing a Bell and Howell Standard Cinemachinery (has plug for use in an electric outlet). (Box 55)
- Series VI. Additional papers. Louise G. Coulson material., Note: Boxes 21-26, 28, and 49 transferred to the Cayuga County Historical Society, July 2018.
  - Louise Coulson, Cayuga county local history, correspondence (Box 27)
  - Files-House Benjamin Built (Box 29)
  - Family files, genealogy files (Box 30)
  - Genealogy (Box 31)
  - Genealogy, correspondence (Box 32)
  - Louise Coulson correspondence, etc. (Box 33)
  - House Benjamin Built, and other typescripts (Box 34)
  - Fordyce family - all typescripts, 1861-1862 diaries of John H. Fordyce, 1864 diary of Louisa Fordyce. Notebooks: Parts I, II, V and VI - winter of mss. On Fordyce family, 1839-1888-1938; 2 notebooks # pp. 1-258, 259-333 [cf. Box 37 for more pp. of mss.]; typescripts of Cayuga Co. church records ie. Reformed Protestant Dutch Church Owasco Outlet (Sand Beach Clr., Fleming). (Box 35)
  - Gayton Family - letters, 1920's and later; clippings, anniversary cards. (Box 36)
  - Fordyce family, L. Coulson's typescripts of Benj. A. Fordyce letters in 1 notebook, annotated typescript of mss. On Fordyce family, pp. 1-1339, in 5 cardboard paper boxes; 1 folder "Notes" 1 folder "Book" (Box 37)
  - Fordyce, Coulson family and personal (Box 38)
  - Fordyce, et al photos (Box 39-40)
  - Fordyce, family papers and miscellaneous (Box 41)
  - Photos (Box 42)
  - Fordyce/Gayton, letters, clippings, deeds, photos, marriage certificate of George L. & Grace Fordyce, estate of N. Horton Fordyce items, silver teaspoon, small leather change purse. (Box 43)
  - Fordyce, genealogy, miscellaneous (Box 44)
  - Unlabled (Box 45)
  - Fordyce, family, miscellaneous (Box 46)
  - (3"leg.) (Box 47)